# MICHAEL BALLARD

# Front End Developer









An ambitious front end developer with 4 years of experience React development, I help create business critical web applications with modern technology from serverless to in house API's, crafting clean responsive UI's for the modern web.

### WORK EXPERIENCE

### Front End Developer

one journey | September 2021-Present

- Helped launch a MLP (Minimum Lovable Product) for an established hospitality agency branching out into the platform space.
- Worked with a team of front end and back end developers to fix bugs, update legacy code and add new features for clients and in house support teams.
- Worked with the design team to craft an in house design system and components library.

#### Front End Lead - Operational Intelligence

Vodafone | July 2020 - August 2021

- Lead front end of in house development for applications used by network engineers and support teams within the UK business.
- Transformed the front end development stack of the team from traditional MVC to React, with a decoupled API backend.
- Created a reusable components library for the team to utilise in order to make development easier as well as getting a consitent look and feel across our web estate.
- Implemented new development tools in the team to enforce coding standards and detect bugs, reducing risk of errors and increasing quality of written code.
- Reduced manual effort by creating CI/CD pipelines for automated testing and deployment of code.
- Ran workshops with the wider organisation to demo our technology transformation, sharing best practices and learnings.

### Graduate Techboost Project - winners

**Vodafone** I December 2019 - July 2020

- Developed a React Native application to provide new starters with a smooth and user friendly onboarding experience.
- Ran workshops for my team to introduce them to mobile app development and React Native.
- $\bullet \quad \text{Led development for the app and helped members of the team with issues they encountered}.\\$
- Took part in UX and UI workshops with senior developers in Vodafone to learn best practice and get feedback from professionals.

# Graduate Solutions Engineer - IoT

**Vodafone** I September 2018 - July 2020

- Developed IoT solutions for customers using JavaScript on our Invent platform.
- Integrated with 3rd party APIs to expand our IoT capability.
- Involvement in client workshops to understand requirements and interate projects in an agile manner.
- Ran workshops with the team to introduce them to various technologies such as React Native, Microsoft Flow and Python programming.
- Delivered a proof of concept using a React front end to integrate with the bespoke javascript engine that ran underneath the IoT platform, enabling IoT solutions to be built using React front ends. This resulted in the department dedicating more resources to front end development, and my React PoC is still being built on to this day.

# Junior Developer

**Gloversure** | August 2016 - May 2017

- My first professional experience of web and mobile app design.
- Developed a mobile app using the lonic framework for customers to be able to manage their site content from their phone.
- Developed a PHP application to enable the marketting team to create mobile notifications for customers.
- Modernised a lot of legacy code. Most noteably AJAXified the CMS to enable dynamic content and less page redirects.
- Discovered React after a friend recommended I look into it, been using it ever since!

## SKILLS

#### Technical

JavaScript, TypeScript, React, NextJS

Serverless/cloud, AWS, GCP

UI/UX

Github, version control, CI/CD pipelines, automated deployment, devops

Docker, containerisation

Chakra UI, custom components libraries

State management, redux, recooil, mobx

Jest, React Testing Library, Playwright

#### **Professional**

Effective communicator

Confident leader

Willingness to help others

Good time management

Agile practices, kanban boards, standups, retrospectives etc.

# Other skills

Photography and Filming

Photoshop and Video editing

Good knowledge of PC Hardware

Inevitably acting as tech support for my whole family

# EDUCATION

# BSc in Computer Science

Aberystwyth University 2014 - 2018

# Warwick School

GCSE and A Level 2007 - 2014

# LANGUAGES

English (Native)

# INTERESTS

Photography

Mountain biking

Gaming

Warhammer

Stock markets and investing

Anything Elon Musk is doing